-==破烂熊乐园倾情奉献==-
本字幕仅供学习交流，严禁用于商业用途
-==http://www.ragbear.com==-
福尔摩斯探案全集 第2季第3集
诺伍德的建筑师
The Norwood Builder
-=Keepfrds MNHD Team=-
校对: ptrpan
谢谢 乔治
Thank you, George.
在刑事专家看来
From the point of view of the criminal expert,
伦敦已经变成一座十分乏味
London has become a singularly odd,
有趣的城市
interesting city.
嗯 我不认为会有很多正派的市民
Well, I hardly think you'll find
同意你的看法
many decent citizens to agree with you.
对 对 我不应该自私
Well, well, well, one must not be selfish.
这对社会有好处
The community's the gain,
除了可怜的专家
and no one the loser say the poor,
无事可做以外 谁也没损失
unfortunate specialist whose occupation was got.
你一定是...
You must havebeen totally...
有前总统文件案...
There's the case of the papers of ex-President...
荷兰轮船"弗里斯兰"号的惊人事件
and shocking affair of the Dutch steamship Treesman,
后者险些害我们丧命
which very nearly cost us both our lives.
它们都成功解决了
Both of them great successes.
很抱歉 福尔摩斯先生不在家
I'm sorry, Mr. Holmes is not at home.
如果我现在见不到他 就会来不及了
If I fail to see him now, it will be too late.
很抱歉 我帮不了你
But I'm sorry, I cannot help you.
但事情真的很紧急
But it is a matter of the utmost urgency.
我已经说过了 年轻人 福尔摩斯先生...
I have already told you, young man, Mr. Holmes ...
福尔摩斯先生
Mr. Holmes!
我一定得见你
Well, I must see you.
我跟这位年轻人说过你不在
I told the young man you weren't here,
但他不听我的
but he wouldn't listen.
对不起 真对不起 我几乎要疯了
I'm sorry, I'm sorry, but I’m nearly out of my mind.
我就是那个倒霉的约翰・赫克托・麦克法兰
I am the unhappy John Hector McFarland.
慢慢告诉我们你是谁
Now, tell us quietly and slowly who you are
有什么需要帮忙的
and what it is that you want.
你刚才只说了自己的名字
You mentioned your name just now
好像我应该认得你似的
as if I should recognize it,
但我确信
but I can assure you,
除了你是个单身汉
beyond the obvious facts that you are a bachelor,
律师 共济会会员 哮喘病患者这些显见事实外
a solicitor and a freemason and an asthmatic,
确实对你一点也不了解
I know nothing about you whatever.
你凌乱的衣服 随身带的那一扎法律文件
Your untidy clothes, sheaf of legal papers,
表链和不规律的喘气声
watch chain and your somewhat irregular breathing.
没错 福尔摩斯先生 你说的就是我
Why, yes, Mr. Holmes, I am all these things.
除此以外 此时此刻
And in addition, I am at this moment,
我还是全伦敦最不幸的人
the most unfortunate man in London.
要是您看过这份报纸的话
I mean, I've ready our newspaper ...
还没看
Not yet.
如果您允许的话 麻烦您念一下
Then, if you would allow me.
昨夜凌晨12点左右
At about 12 o’clock last night,
下诺伍德发生一起意外事件
an instance occurred at Lower Norwood which points,
恐是严重犯罪行为
it is feared, to a serious crime.
一住宅背后的小贮木场起火
A small timber yard caught fire at the back of a house
该住宅属于建筑师约纳斯・奥德克所有
belonging to Mr. Jonas Oldacre, a builder.
火灾现场未见户主 令人诧异
Surprise was expressed at Mr. Oldacre's absence,
显然户主已失踪
and it became apparent he had disappeared.
检查卧室
An examination of his room
保险柜门已开
revealed a safe which was open,
现场有激烈打斗的迹象
signs of a murderous struggle,
一沉重的手杖
and a heavy walking stick
柄上沾有血迹
with stains of blood upon the handle.
正如我们...
As we ...
我只求您不要离弃我
All I ask is that you don't abandon me.
我在伦敦桥站刚下车就被跟踪
A man has followed me from London Bridge Station.
要是我还没把话讲完以前他们来逮捕我的话
If they arrest me before I finish my story,
务必请您告诉他们给我时间
make them give me time
把全部事实告诉您
so that I may tell you the whole truth.
只要知道有您在外面为我奔走
I could go to jail happy
我可以高高兴兴地走进监狱
if I knew that you were outside working for me.
逮捕你?
Arrest you?
这的确太有意思了
This is really most gratifying.
你会因什么罪名被逮捕呢?
On what charge do you expect to be arrested?
以谋杀下诺伍德
Upon the charge of murdering
约纳斯・奥德克的罪名
Mr. Jonas Oldacre of Lower Norwood.
天啊!
Dear me!
本报付印时
As we go to press,
案件已出现惊人的发展
sensational development shave been reported.
在火场灰烬中
Charred remain shave been found
找到被烧焦的残骸
among the ashes of the fire,
根据警方推测
and the police theory is that the victim
受害者被木棍击毙 尸体被焚烧灭迹
was clubbed to death and the body ignited.
现已查明奥德克先生
It is known that Mr. Oldacre
是夜曾接待来客
received a visitor last night,
该手杖已确认
and the stick has been identified
属于来访者
as belonging to that person,
伦敦一年轻的律师
a young London solicitor,
名为约翰・赫克托・麦克法兰
by the name of John Hector McFarland.
麦克法兰先生 我想先问一下 你怎么仍逍遥法外呢?
May I ask why you are still at liberty, Mr. McFarland,
既然表面上已经有足够证据
as there seems to be enough evidence
可以逮捕你了
to justify your arrest?
我和母亲同住在
I live with my mother,
布莱克希斯多林顿寓所
at Torrington Lodge in Black heath,
但是昨晚
but last night,
有点事要替奥德克先生办
having late business with Mr. Oldacre,
我在诺伍德一家旅馆住下来
I stayed at a hotel in Norwood.
福尔摩斯先生 我对此事毫不知情
Mr. Holmes, I knew nothing of this affair
直到今天早上乘火车回办公室途中
until I was on the train to my office this morning
看到报纸上您刚才听过的新闻
and read what you have just heard.
我立即看出自己的处境非常威胁
I saw at once the terrible danger of my position
就赶来把这件案子委托给你
and hurried to put the case in your hands.
哎呀 雷斯垂德巡官
Ah, Inspector Le Strade,
我们都在等着你呢
we have been expecting you.
福尔摩斯先生?
Mr. Holmes?
华生先生?
Dr. Watson?
约翰・赫克托・麦克法兰先生?
Mr. John Hector McFarland?
是的
Yes.
由于你蓄意谋杀下诺伍德的
I arrest you for the willful murder
约纳斯・奥德克先生 我现在逮捕你
of Mr. Jonas Oldacreof Lower Norwood.
等等 再等一会
Hold up, just one moment.
再等半个小时左右
A half an hour more or less
对你来说不会有什么影响吧
could make little difference to you,
这位年轻绅士正要给我们讲述
and this young gentleman was about to give us an account
这桩非常有趣事件的经过
of this very interesting affair,
也许能帮助我们把事情弄清楚
which might aid usin clearing it up.
我觉得弄清楚整件事再容易不过了
There will be no difficulty in clearing it up,
谢谢 福尔摩斯先生
thank you,Mr. Holmes.
不过 如果你允许的话
Nevertheless, I think with your permission,
我倒很有兴趣听听他的说法
I would be much interested in hearing his account.
好吧 福尔摩斯先生
Well, Mr. Holmes,
我很难拒绝你的要求
there's no denying that you have been
因为过去你给我们
of use to the force
帮过一两次忙 但我必须...
once or twice in the past,but I must insist ...
我只请求您一定要听我讲
All I ask is that you should hear
而且明白我讲的绝对是真话
and recognizethe absolute truth.
我给你半个小时
I'll give youhalf an hour.
请坐 麦克法兰先生
Sit down, McFarland.
谢谢 雷斯垂德先生
Thank you, Le Strade.
我得先提醒你 你现在所说的话
We must warn you with what you say now
都会成为不利于你的证据
will appear in evidence against you.
请继续
Pray continue.
我必须先说明我对约纳斯・奥德克先生
I must first explain that I knew nothing
一点都不了解
of Mr. Jonas Oldacre,
虽然他的名字很熟悉
although his name was familiar to me.
很多年以前 我父母和他认识
Many years ago, my parents were acquainted with him,
但后来逐渐疏远了
but ... well,they drifted apart.
因此 昨天下午大约三点钟
And so it came as a complete surprise
他走进我城里的办公室的时候
when yesterday afternoon,at about 3 o'clock,
我感到很奇怪
he walked into my office in the city.
奥德克先生 下午好
Mr. Oldacre,good afternoon,
我是麦克法兰
I'm Mr. McFarland.
你是否介意过来一趟呢?
Would you care to come through?
请先坐下
Please, won't you sit down?
我有什么能为您服务的呢?
How can I help you?
这是我遗嘱的草稿
This is a draft of my Will.
我希望由你 麦克法兰先生
I want you,Mr. McFarland,
按照正式法定的格式把它写出来
to cast it into proper legal shape.
你写的时候 我就在这里坐着
I shall sit here while you do so.
您可以想象出来我的惊讶 福尔摩斯先生
You can understand my astonishment, Mr. Holmes,
当我看到他除了若干保留外
when I found that, with some minor reservations,
把其余的全部财产都留给我
his entire estate had been left to me.
但我真的不明白
But I ... I simply don't understand.
好吧 我来简单说明一下
Well, then,let me explain.
我是个单身汉 麦克法兰先生
I'm a bachelor,Mr. McFarland,
我没多少亲属
with few relatives,
没人值得我考虑的
and none who deserve my consideration.
唉 那样说也太...
Well, that may well be so ...
先听我说完
Let me ...let me finish.
请原谅
I beg your pardon.
近年来 我已经逐渐不问世事
For many years now, I've with drawn from my business.
我是建筑师 我敢夸口
I was a builder, and though I say it myself,
我在这个领域是出类拔萃的
an extremely successful one.
成功地赢得可观的财富
Successful enough to have gained considerable
过着离群索居
and thus live out my life in complete,
而又舒适的生活
if solitary,comfort.
很多年前 我遇到你母亲
Many years ago,I knew your mother.
相遇相知 想娶她为妻
Knew her,and hoped to marry her.
后来她嫁给你父亲
Then she met and married your father.
我完全不知情
I had no idea.
当然 你怎么可能知道呢?
Well,and why should you?
三个月前
Three months ago, why,
我听说你父亲
I read of your father's death
死于布莱克希斯
in The Daily Telegraph,
我就想到了你母亲
and my mind was turned to your mother
还有你这个本可能成为我儿子的年轻人
and to the son who might very well have been my own.
这是我让你生活无忧的方式
This is my way of securing your future.
我知道我留下的东西
I know that whatever I leave
能落在值得信任的人手中
will be in worthy hands.
除了感谢之外 我真不知道能说些什么
What can I say,but thank you?
这里有些字据 我想该让你过目
There are a few documents I think you should see ...
租约 房契
building leases,title deeds,
抵押凭证等等
mortgages and so on.
既然我已经拿定主意
Well, now my mind's made up,
在所有事情办完之后才能放心
I shan't rest easy until the whole thing's settled.
是的 理应如此
Yes, of course.
请在今晚来我家一趟
I beg you to come to my house tonight.
晚上9点如何?
What shall we say,9 o'clock?
G 没问题
Why, yes.
把遗嘱的定稿带过来
You'll of course bring the finalized Will,
我们就能把所有的事情都安排妥当
and then we can settle the matter once and for all.
是的 当然
Yes, of course.
谢谢你 孩子
Thank you,my boy.
噢 还有一件事
Oh, one last thing.
在一切事情还没有办完以前
Not a word of this to your dear mother
什么话都不要和你母亲说
until everything is settled.
我想给她一个小小的意外惊喜
I want it to be a little surprised for her.
小小的 我...
Little, I ...
你答应吗?
You ...you promise?
我向您保证
You have my word.
为了这次会面我提早出发
I left in good time for my appointment,
但那栋房子太难找了
but had difficulty in finding the house,
当我到他家的时候快9点半了
so that it was nearly half-past before I reached it.
晚上好
Good evening.
我和奥德克先生有约
I have an appointment with Mr. Oldacre.
你是麦克法兰先生吗?
Mr. McFarland?
对 就是我
Yes, that's right.
那算不上很热情的接待
It was not the warmest of receptions.
房子有一种怪异的 冷淡的气氛
And the house itself had a peculiar, unloved feeling.
抱歉让你久等了 孩子
Sorry to keep you waiting, my boy.
别客气 先生
Not at all, sir.
请恕我来晚了
I'm a little late,I'm afraid.
你把文件都带来了吧?
Now, you brought the papers?
是的 没错      很好
Yes, indeed.        Excellent.
卧室在一楼
The bedroom was on the ground floor
那里有个大的保险柜
where there was a large safe.
把其余文件都拿过来吧 我的孩子
Bring the rest of those papers, my boy.
现在开始工作吧
Now, to business.
一切都办妥了吧?
All done?
是的 先生 都办妥了
Yes, sir,all done.
瞧这时间啊 我的孩子
Just seen the time,my boy.
你得回家了
You must get home.
噢 谢谢你
Oh, thank you.
我来的时候还带着一根手杖的
I had a stick with me.
哎呀 不知道她放哪去了
Ah, I wonder where she put it?
一根很厚实的手杖
A rather heavy walking stick.
是父亲留给我的
It belonged to my father.
哎呀 不要紧 我会好好保管
Ah, never mind, I'll take good care of it
等你下次来取
until we meet again.
毕竟从现在起 应该能经常见到你
After all, I shall be seeing a great deal of you now, I hope.
我们能经常见面的 先生
Indeed you shall, sir.
我离开了他
I left him there.
保险柜是开着的
The safe was open,
那些字据还摆在桌上
and the documents were on his desk.
已经太晚 回不去布莱克希斯了
It was too late to go back to Blackheath,
所以我在诺伍德的旅馆里住了一晚
and so I spent the night at a hotel in Norwood.
在今天早上以前 我对这起可怕的事件
I knew nothing more of this horrible affair
一无所知
until this morning.
你手上还有奥德克先生带给你的
Do you have the original draft of the Will
遗嘱草稿吗?
that Oldacre brought to you?
G 是的 我带过来了
Why, yes, I ...I have it here.
巡官 能把这些草稿借给我看一天吗?
May I retain this for 24 hours, Inspector?
假如能对你有所启发的话
It would amuse you.
你还有别的要问吗 福尔摩斯先生?
Well, anything more you'd like to ask, Mr. Holmes?
在我去布莱克希斯前 没什么要问的了
Not until I've been to Blackheath.
你是说去诺伍德以前吧?
You mean Norwood?
啊 对了 我要说的是诺伍德
No doubt, that is what I must have meant.
好吧 麦克法兰先生
Now, Mr. McFarland,
我的警士就站在门口
my Constable's at the door,
外面还有辆四轮马车在等着
there's a four-wheeler waiting.
早安 先生
Morning, gentlemen.
早安
Morning.
这份遗嘱的确有些特点
There are certain points about this document,
华生 你看呢?
are there not Watson?
嗯 我能看出头两行
Well, I can read the first two lines
还有第二页中间几句
and these in the middle of the second page
还有最后一两行
and one or two at the end,
就跟印上去的一样清晰
I mean, they're as clear as print.
但其余部分都写得不清楚
But the writing in between is very bad,
有几处地方根本看不出写的是什么
and there's several places where I can't read it at all.
你怎么解释这一点呢?
What do make of that?
你怎么解释呢?
What do you make of it?
是在火车上写的
That it was written on the train.
清晰的部分是火车停站的时候写的
The good writing represents stations,
模糊的部分是火车行驶时写的 最不清晰的部分...
the bad writing movement,and the very bad writing ...
是火车经过岔道时写的?
Passing over the points?
有经验的专家能马上断定
A scientific expert would pronounce at once
这是在一条郊区铁路线上写的
that it was drawn upon a suburban line.
因为
Since nowhere,
只有在大城市附近
save in the immediate vicinity of a great city,
才会有接二连三的岔道
could there be so quick a succession of points.
假如他花了整个旅程的时间
Granting that his whole journey
来起草这份遗嘱
was occupied in drawing up the Will,
那必定是一趟快车
then the train must have been an express,
在诺伍德和伦敦桥之间只停过一次
stopping only once between Norwood and London Bridge.
没错 但这实在是太奇怪了
Yes, but it's curious,is it not,
一个人居然会以这么随便的方式
that a man should draw up so important a document
来写一份这么重要的文件?
in so haphazard fashion?
这说明他实际上
And it suggests that he thought
并不重视这份遗嘱
it was going to be of no practical importance.
这等于他同时给自己出了一张死刑判决书
Well, he drew up his death warrant at the same time.
这件案件对我来说还不是很清楚
This case is not clear to me.
走吧 华生
Come, Watson!
我们去哪呢 诺伍德?
Where are we going,Norwood?
不 布莱克希斯
No, Blackheath.
走吧!
Come!
我儿是天底下最敦厚良善的人
My son's the gentlest creature on God's earth.
我绝不相信他会犯下
It's inconceivable he could even contemplate
如此严重的罪行
such a terrible crime.
他根本不认识这个人 福尔摩斯先生
He didn't even know the man, Mr. Holmes.
但你认识他 麦克法兰夫人
But you did,Mrs. McFarland.
多年以前的事了
Years ago.
我几乎忘记了他的存在
I'd forgotten that he ever existed.
我尝试去忘却
I tried to forget.
但要忘记像约纳斯・奥德克这样的人
It's impossible to quite forget
是不可能的
a man like Jonas Oldacre.
是的 我很了解他
Yes, I knew him well.
曾经 我们几乎订婚结为夫妇
At one time, we were engaged to be married.
谢天谢地我还有眼力离开他
Thank heaven I had the sense to turn away from him
跟一个也许比他穷 但比他更好的人结了婚
and marry a better,if poorer, man.
噢 请坐
Oh, please.
你丈夫最近去世了?
Your husband died recently?
他是一个宽容 温和的人
He was a kind man,gentle man.
他是和约纳斯・奥德克完全不一样的人
He was everything Jonas Oldacre was not.
然而 你曾经考虑过嫁给他?
And yet, at one time,you were prepared to marry him?
我说过我熟悉他
I said that I knew him well,
我越了解他
but the more I knew of him,
就越意识到
the more I came to realize
自己根本不清楚他的为人
I knew him not at all.
他会突然性情大变 还会恐吓我
He would change suddenly,would also frighten me.
在他性格里有阴暗的一面 福尔摩斯先生
There was a dark side to his character, Mr. Holmes.
想要制造痛苦的欲望
A desire to cause pain.
我自己的照片
My own photograph.
是送给他的第一份礼物
It was my first present to him.
天哪!
Good heavens!
在我结婚的那天
That was how it was returned to me
他把照片弄成这样还给我
on my wedding day,
附着一张卑劣的纸条
together with a vile note
疯狂地诅咒我的家人
urging a curse upon my house
说他永远都不会原谅我
and saying he'd never forgive me.
不过 看上去他现在宽恕你了...
And yet, he does seem to have forgiven you ...
毕竟他把自己的全部财产留给了你的儿子
after all, to leave his entire estate to your son.
我儿子和我都不要那个恶人的
Neither my son nor I want anything
任何东西 不管他是死是活
from that wicked man,dead or alive.
麦克法兰夫人 事实是
Mrs. McFarland,the fact remains
遗嘱已经拟好
that the Will was made.
我只不过不明白
I simply can't understand it.
为什么?
Why?
你有向儿子谈论过奥德克先生的事吗?
Had you ever spoken of Oldacre to your son?
也许提到过刚才告诉我们的事实?
I mean, perhaps told him what you've just told me now?
不 从未说过
No, never.
从来没有?
Never?
他看到了照片
He found the photograph.
先夫想轻描淡写说一下就算了
My husband tried to make light of it,
但他坚持要知道缘由
but he insisted.
先夫将部分事实真相告诉他 仅此而已
My husband told him something of the truth, that's all.
这孩子听了之后很不安吗?
And the boy was disturbed?
他很自然会心烦意乱
He was upset,naturally.
情况是这样的 麦克法兰夫人 警方可能会认为
You see, Mrs. McFarland,what the police might say is,
他听闻了奥德克先生对你的所作所为
that he had heard of Oldacre's behavior toward you.
自然会产生憎恨之心 犯下暴行
It would pre-dispose him toward hatred and violence.
该案对他的指控
And so that case against him would be
就有更强而有力的依据了
considerably strengthened.
不
No.
主在天堂俯视众生 福尔摩斯先生
There is a God in heaven, Mr. Holmes,
主终会惩罚这个邪恶的人
and that same God who's punished that wicked man
只争迟与早
will show in his own good time,
我儿手上确实没沾染过血污
my son's hands are guiltless of his blood.
请在这儿等我一下
Wait here, please.
福尔摩斯先生 华生先生
Mr. Holmes, Dr. Watson.
我们刚刚清理完毕
We're just clearing up.
这是我之前借阅的遗嘱
The Will as promised.
看 纽扣
Look, buttons!
裤子的纽扣
Trouser buttons.
很可能 你有带放大镜过来吗?
No doubt, you've brought your glass with you?
上面的名字是海安姆
The name is Hiams.
据管家勒克辛顿太太说 海安姆
According to Mrs. Lexington,the housekeeper, Hiams,
是奥德克先生的裁缝的姓氏
is the name of Mr. Oldacre's tailor.
想必燃烧过后的有机体残骸
Presumably, the organic remains
已经送去实验室化验了吧?
have been removed to the laboratory?
是的 医生
They have, Doctor,
虽然未必能派上什么用场
though they'll be of little use, I suspect.
这个倒霉的家伙早已烧成灰烬
The poor devil was no more than bone and cinder.
对凶手来说多么方便啊
How very convenient for the murderer.
虽然对奥德克先生来说可不怎么方便
Not I might venture for Mr. Oldacre.
虽然如此 巡官 好歹是骨头渣子啊
Nevertheless, Inspector,bones cinder.
谢天谢地  幸好他还穿着裤子
Thank heavens, he was wearing his trousers.
那根手杖的确是属于被告的
This stick belongs to the accused,
他也承认了
and he's never denied it.
他声称离开房子的时候
He says that he could not find it
找不到那根手杖
when he came to leave the house.
一面之词 福尔摩斯先生 一面之词
Says, Mr. Holmes, says.
我的技术人员在地毯上
My experts made out footmarks
找到两组脚印
of both men on the carpet.
之后有无数人踏足此处
And too much subsequent traffic
所以我基本上查不出什么来
to make any examination on my part worthwhile.
有两组脚印 福尔摩斯先生
Two sets of footmarks,Mr. Holmes.
没有第三者的脚印
None of any third person.
给你们布的又一个疑阵
Another trick for your side.
依我看 这些字据都是从保险柜里拿出来的吧?
I suppose all these papers are from the safe?
没错
Correct.
没有 没有任何东西
And nothing,absolutely nothing,
被移动过?
has been removed?
什么都没有
Nothing whatsoever.
如你所见 有一两封已经拆开
We have opened one or two,as you can see,
来检查里面的内容
to check the contents.
我可以看看吗?
May I check them?
当然可以
By all means.
我还得回苏格兰场办点事
I, myself, have business at The Yard.
对了 我想见一下女管家
Oh, and I would like to see the housekeeper ...
她叫什么名字?
what is her name?
勒克辛顿太太
Mrs. Lexington.
她也提供不了什么新情况
She'll add nothing more to what you already know.
还是让我见见吧
Nevertheless.
我让她进来吧
I'll send her in.
难道这会成为
Could it be that for once
雷斯垂德有史以来第一次胜利?
Le Strade is on the right track?
我的所有直觉都指向一个方向
All my instincts are one way,
事情另有隐衷
and all the facts are the other.
先生 你要见我?
You wish to see me, sir?
是的 勒克辛顿太太
Yes,Mrs. Lexington
这位是我的挚友及同事
this is my friend and colleague,
华生医生
Dr. Watson.
请坐
Do sit down.
如果可以的话 请容许我站着
I'll stand,if I may.
这房间让我觉得不太舒服
This room has no comfort for me.
你让麦克法兰先生进来的时候是9点半吗?
You let young Mr. McFarland into this house at 9:30?
是的
Yes.
当时我该好好考虑一下的
I wish that my hand had withered before I'd done so.
你在什么时候上床休息的呢?
And you retired to bed at?
十一点二十分
20 minutes past 11:00.
你什么都没听到吗?
And you heard nothing?
我的房间在房子另一头
My room is at the far end of the house.
在火警响起前什么都没听到
I heard nothing until the fire alarm sounded.
就在那个时候
It was then,only then,
我意识到不幸的主人已经被谋害了
that I realized my poor master had been murdered.
勒克辛顿太太 据你所知
Mrs. Lexington,to your knowledge,
你的主人有仇人吗?
did your master have any enemies?
谁没有仇人呢
Every man has his enemies.
像奥德克先生这样的生意人
And a businessman like Mr. Oldacre,
也许仇家就更多了 是吧?
more than most,perhaps?
他是一位受人尊敬的绅士
He was a well-respected gentleman
一直独来独往
who kept himself very much to himself.
你对这些字据是否知情?
Do you know anything about these papers?
我对奥德克先生的私人事务
I know nothing
一无所知
of Mr. Oldacre'sprivate affairs.
警方在灰烬里发现的纽扣呢?
The buttons that the police found in the fire?
主人有三套衣服是由海安姆先生缝制的
My master had three suits made by Mr. Hiams ...
两套在衣橱里
two are still in that wardrobe there,
第三套当天晚上他穿在身上
and the third he was wearing that night.
谢谢你 勒克辛顿太太
Thank you,Mrs. Lexington,
你非常很合作
you have been most cooperative.
你觉得她怎么样?
What do you make of her?
守口如瓶 依我看
Tight as wax,if you ask me,
但也许这只是她一贯的作风
but then, perhaps that's her usual manner?
我知道一切都不对 我从骨子里感受到
It's all wrong,I feel it in my bones,
还有些重要情况是我们一无所知的
something ... something has not come out,
而女管家是知道的
and that woman knows it.
福尔摩斯 能让我看看这些字据吗?
Holmes, would you like me to have a look at these papers?
一个人的银行账号所透露的信息
Well, a man's bank account can tell us
就和日记所泄露的一样多
as much as his diary.
没错
Correct.
谢谢 华生
Thank you, Watson.
没事的 警官
It's all right Constable,
我只是舒展一下腿脚而已
I'm just stretching my legs.
我会看着他们的
I'll watch them.
啊 警官
Ah, Constable.
你是本地人吗?
Are you a local man?
我在伦敦桥出生 先生 离这儿半公里
Born on Bridge, sir,not a half-mile from here.
太好了
Excellent.
你能给我提供一点当地的消息吗?
Then perhaps you can offer me some local knowledge?
我会尽力而为的 先生
I'll do my best,sir,
一定尽我所能
I'll most certainly do my best.
福尔摩斯!
Holmes!
雷斯垂德确实说过字据都没有被动过吧?
Le Strade did say that no documents had been removed?
是的
Yes.
我也觉得他没动过
That's what I thought.
你有什么发现吗?
You've found something?
没有 一无所获才令我觉得很奇怪
No, it's what I haven't found that interests me.
比对过后发现
There are certain cross-references
确实发生过几笔交易 金额颇大的交易
to various deeds,valuable deeds,
但找不到凭证
none of which I can find.
但有一事相当明确
But one thing is clear:
我们有理由相信
Oldacre was hardly
奥德克先生的境况
in the affluent circumstances
并不是太富裕
we have been led to believe.
他的银行帐户余额所剩无几
His bank account was practically empty,
主要是因为过去一年里
largely because he had made several large payments
他开了几张大额支票给柯尼利亚斯先生
in the past year to a certain Mr. Cornelius.
麦克法兰先生实际上一无所得
Young McFarland would have inherited nothing.
此事大有蹊跷
This is of interest.
为什么一个退隐的建筑师
Why should a retired builder
会和这位柯尼利亚斯先生有这样的大宗交易呢?
have such large transactions with a Mr. Cornelius?
嗳 我们坐车回城
Well, let's take our cab,
看看能不能从他的银行账号里找到什么线索
and see what we can find out from his city bank.
一起吗?
You coming?
我想再多留一会
I'll stay here for a while.
诺伍德火车站
Norwood Station.
那么 你不打算和朋友
So, you're not going back to London
一起回伦敦了?
with your friend,then?
不 暂时先不回去
No, not yet,anyway.
希望我的存在不会给你造成不便
I do hope my presence doesn't inconvenience you.
顺便提一下 我应当警告你一下
By the way,I should warn you,
我发现有形迹可疑的人在大门窥视
I found an undesirable lurking about by the gates.
我看到他...
I saw him on ...
形迹可疑的人
An undesirable?
一个流浪汉 勒克辛顿太太
A tramp,Mrs. Lexington,
流落街头的男人
a gentlemen of the road.
我什么都给不了他
He will get nothing here.
啊 你不认为应该对
Ah, you don't believe in
比我们不幸的人伸出援手吗?
supporting our less fortunate brethren?
我能养活自己 他们也理应如此
I work,so can they.
的确是这样
Quite so.
我在去克莱克斯顿的路上
I'm on my way to Croxton.
我已经流浪够了
I've done enough walking,I have...
走遍各个地方
To all kinds of places.
就留在这里吧
I'll stay put.
我曾在这里和朋友会面
I used to meet a friend of mine here.
噢 你可能会认识他 他是个海员
Oh, you might know him,he's a seafaring man.
阿哈 我知道有这么个人
Ah-ha I know him
和我一起睡了四晚的人 就是他
Shared my billet for the last four nights, he does.
之后他就一言不发地离开了
And off he goes,without even a word.
你听我的话
You take my tip.
和他撇清关系
Stay clear of him.
他是个骗子
He's a liar.
他可没有这样对待过我
He didn't strike me as such.
他去过那个大房子里 他去了
He goes up to that big house, he does.
他回来之后就瞎扯淡
He comes back here and tells some yarn
说和那里的老先生聊得很欢
about him putting out with old mans,
那位先生让他第二天再过去
and telling him to come back tomorrow
说是会给他一点食物
and they'll give him some grub
还有几件旧衣物
and some cast-offs for him.
嗯 这怎么算是撒谎呢?
Well,how is that lying?
因为 我的朋友
Because,my friend,
我也曾经去过一次
I already paid my call.
结果几乎被打死
I nearly got my lord on my back
说我厚颜无耻
for my insolence ...
无礼之极
insolence.
也许他说的故事更讨人喜欢
Perhaps he told you a pleasing tale.
你是说
Are you saying,
一个醉酒的船员比我这个22军团的军士
that a drunken sailor has more to offer
还有办法?
than a Sergeant in the 22nd?
不 不
No, no.
他是个骗子
He's a liar.
他说 "无论我得到什么"
He says, Whatever I get,he says,
"我都会和你一起分享的 伙计" 他是这样说的
I'll share with you,shipmate,  he says.
之后他就走了
Off he goes.
从此不见踪影
Not a sight of him since.
福尔摩斯
Holmes,
你得先吃点东西啊
you must permit yourself some food.
一定得吃
You must eat.
我现在匀不出精力
A present, I cannot afford energy
来消化食物
and nerve force for digestion.
嗳 如果你还想继续调查这件案子就得吃啊
Well, you must if you intend to pursue this case.
我感觉 我的朋友
I feel,my dear fellow,
这件案子将不光彩地以雷斯垂德
that our case will end ingloriously
吊死咱们的委托人来结束
by Le Strade hanging our client,
这对苏格兰场无疑会成为一次胜利
which will certainly be atriumph for Scotland Yard.
来了一份电报
There's a telegram.
新获重要证据
Important fresh evidence at hand,
麦克法兰罪行已定
McFarland's guilt definitely established,
奉劝放弃此案 雷斯垂德
advise you to abandoncase, Le Strade.
这是雷斯垂德自鸣得意的小胜利
It is Le Strade's little cockle-doodle of victory.
我们先吃早饭吧
Let's have some breakfast,
然后一块出去看看有什么可做的
and then go out together and see what we can do.
今天我觉得需要你的陪伴
I feel as if I shall need your company
和精神援助
and moral support today.
啊 福尔摩斯先生 华生医生
Ah, Mr. Holmes,Dr. Watson.
我想这次你们得承认
I think you will acknowledge
我们走在你前头了
that we're just a little in front of you this time.
请到这边来 先生们
Step this way, if you please, gentlemen,
我想我能彻底说服你们
and I'm sure I can convince you
约翰・麦克法兰
that it was John McFarland
就是本案的真凶
who committed this crime.
我们都讨厌自己是错的那一方
I don't like being wrong anymore than the rest of us do.
但是 一个人总不能
Still, a man can't always
指望事事如意
expect to have it his own way,
是不是这样 华生医生?
can he Dr. Watson?
这就是女管家放置
This is where the housekeeper left
麦克马兰先生手杖的地方
McFarland's hatand stick,
也是他作案之后必定过来
and this is also where he would have come
拿回自己帽子的地方
to collect his hat after the crime was committed.
现在看看这个
Now, look at this.
一个大拇指纹
A thumb mark.
正如我观察到的
So I observe.
带血的大拇指纹
A thumb mark in blood.
你知道大拇指的指纹没有两个同样的
You are aware that no two thumb marks are alike?
我听说过类似这样的话
I have heard something of the kind.
一模一样
Identical.
这是今天早上从麦克法兰手上取来的
And that was taken from McFarland this morning.
绝对是同一个大拇指印出来的
Definitely the same thumb mark.
这是决定性的
And that is final.
是决定性的
Quite final.
是谁作出这个惊人的发现的?
Who made this discovery?
是女管家勒克辛顿太太
It was Mrs. Lexington here
告诉我的警士的
who drew my Constable's attention to it.
我想
And, I suppose,
很可能这血迹昨天就在墙上吧?
there is no doubt that the mark was there yesterday?
嗳 当然麦克法兰会深夜
Well, of course McFarland could have crept out
从监狱里跑出来
of jail in the middle of the night
增加对自己不利的证据
just to strengthen the evidence against himself.
哈哈
Ha-ha.
你不会反对我到楼上转转吧?
Have you any objection if I take a stroll upstairs?
不 请便
No, none at all.
可是上面什么都没有
There's nothing up there, though.
情况看起来很不利 福尔摩斯
So many things look so bad, Holmes.
但这个证据中有一个十分严重的缺陷
But there is a serious flaw in this new evidence.
什么缺陷?
What's that?
昨天我检查门厅的时候
That thumb print was not there
墙上并没有血指纹
when I examined the hall yesterday.
雷斯垂德警官
Inspector Le Strade,
我觉得你的证据不充足
I cannot help thinking your evidence is incomplete.
你是什么意思呢 福尔摩斯先生?
What do you mean,Mr. Holmes?
我只是要说有一个重要的证人
Merely that there is an important witness
你还没有见到
that you have not yet seen.
你能引见一下这位证人吗?
You can produce this witness, can you?
我想我能
I think I can.
那么 请让他出来吧
Well then, do so.
我尽力而为
I'll do my best.
你有几个警士?
How many Constables have you?
能马上召集来的有三个
Three within call.
好极了
Excellent.
他们都是体型健壮
I assume that they are able-bodied,
声音洪亮的大个子吧?
large men with powerful voices?
他们当然是
No doubt that they are,yeah.
外面的小屋里有一大堆麦秸
In the outhouse, there is a quantity of straw.
请你们搬两捆进来
I would like two bundles brought in.
麦秸?
Straw?
再提两桶水
And two buckets of water.
水?
Water?
把东西都带到顶层平台上
Ask them to bring it to the top landing.
麦秸放进壁炉 往前一点
Straw, into the fireplace,a little bit in front.
两桶水放到那边 警官
Two buckets of water to that side, Constable.
福尔摩斯先生!
Mr. Holmes!
我不知道你是不是在跟我们开玩笑
I don't know whether you'replaying a game with us,
可以照直跟我们说 不用故弄玄虚
but surely tell us without all this tom-foolery.
我向你保证 雷斯垂德
I can assure you,Le Strade,
我做每件事都有完全理由的
I have an excellent reason for everything that I do.
华生 你点着麦秸好吗?
Watson, would you put a match to that straw?
警官 到时麻烦你用水把火扑灭好吗?
And Constable, will you sprinkle it with water?
现在 我们来看看
Now, we must see
能不能给你找出那个证人来 雷斯垂德
if we can find this witness for you, Le Strade.
先生们
Gentlemen,
你们跟我一起大喊着火 好吗 ?
would you please join meand we'll call a fire ...
一 二 三 "着火啦!"
one, two three ...FIRE!
"着火啦!"
Fire.
我们还能喊得更大声一点
We can do better than that.
一起敞开嗓门大喊吧
Full voice,and together.
"着火啦!"
FIRE!
天哪
Good heavens,
警官 拿一桶水洒在麦秸上吧
Constable, a bucket of water on that straw.
雷斯垂德 请允许我向你介绍
Le Strade, allow me to present you
这就是本案失踪的重要证人 约纳斯・奥德克先生
with your missing principal witness, Mr. Jonas Oldacre.
这是怎么回事?
What's this then?
你这些时候在干什么?
What have you been doing all this time?
我没有害人
I've done no harm.
没害人?
NO harm!
你想尽一切办法
You've only done your best
要把一个无辜的人送上绞架
to get an innocent man hanged.
要不是有这位先生的话
If it wasn't for this gentleman standing here,
说不定你就得逞了
I'm not sure you wouldn't have succeeded.
把他带下去!
Take him!
让咱们看看这只耗子之前躲在什么地方
Let us see where this rat has been lurking.
这就是做建筑师的有利条件
Now you see the advantage of being a builder,
能给自己打造一个隐秘的藏身之所
he was able to fix up his own little hiding place
而不需要任何人帮手
without any confederate,
当然他那个女管家除外
save for that precious housekeeper of his,
我应该马上把她也放进你的猎囊 巡官
whom I should lose no time in adding to your bag, Inspector.
这些就是遗失的字据吧?
And these are the missing papers, no doubt?
显然如此
No doubt what so ever.
警官 把女管家找来
Constable, find the housekeeper.
你是怎么想到这个地方的 福尔摩斯先生?
How did you know about that place, Mr. Holmes?
当我对比这个房间
When I compared the proportions of this room
和楼下房间的比例时
with those of the room below,
我推测壁炉的墙是假的
I deduced that this fireplace wall was false.
奥德克虽然胆量过人
Oldacre clearly had a great deal of nerve,
但却没有足够勇气
but little enough,I've found,
能在火警面前呆着不动
to like quiet before an alarm of fire.
但是你究竟是怎么知道
How in the world did you know
他藏在屋里的呢?
that he was in the house at all?
那枚拇指印 雷斯垂德
The thumb mark,Le Strade.
我昨天检查大厅的时候 墙上确实什么都没有
When I examined the hall yesterday, it was clear.
因此 指印是后来在夜里按上去的
Therefore, it must have been put there during the night.
怎么按上去的呢?
But how?
当晚麦克法兰检查字据后
After McFarland had examined the papers that night,
封存字据
he resealed them.
那样就在封蜡上留下了姆指纹
To do so, he used his thumb upon the wax.
在密室盘算一切的时候
Brooding in that den of his,
奥德克灵机一动
it suddenly struck Oldacre
想到可以好好利用那枚指纹
what use he could make of that thumbprint.
在蜡模上抹上血迹
Smearing the wax with a little blood,
以此制造出足以证明
he made what appeared to be absolutely
麦克法兰有罪的确证
damning evidence against McFarland.
但他制造这个大骗局的苦心是什么呢?
But what was the object of his deception?
你看 是这么回事 警官
Ah, well,you see Inspector,
为了骗过那些紧追不放的
in order to swindle his creditors,
所有债主
who were pressing him,
奥德克通过给某柯尼利亚斯先生开出大额支票的方式
Oldacre emptied his bank account by paying out
清空了自己的银行帐户
several large sums to acertain Mr. Cornelius.
现在我可以认定奥德克先生
Now, I have no doubt that Messers Oldacre
和柯尼利亚斯先生是同一个人
and Cornelius are one and the same person,
改名换姓的目的
the object being to change his name,
就是取出所有款项 然后销声匿迹
draw on the money,and then vanish.
我们所面对的 是一个
We see before us a very deep,
非常恶毒 报复心强的人
malicious and vindictive man.
你是否知道麦克法兰的母亲
Did you know that he was once refused
从前拒绝过他的求婚?
by McFarland's mother?
他终其一生都渴望报复
All his life, he has longed for vengeance.
假如能让人误认为
If he could give the impression
他是被旧情人的
that he was murdered
独子谋杀了
by the only child of his former sweetheart,
还有比这更好的报复方式吗?
what more better revenge?
我绝对不会允许有任何实质性伤害
I would never have allowed any real harm
发生在麦克法兰先生身上
to befall poor Mr. McFarland,
我向你保证
I assure you.
那要留待陪审团来决定
That's for the jury to decide.
你要控告我?
You're charging me?
为了一个恶作剧?
For a joke?
只不过是一个恶作剧而已
It's nothing more than a practical joke.
这可是 谋杀啊...
It's nothing less than murder ...
记得火灾里的尸体吗
the body in the fire.
那是谁的尸体?
But whose body was it?
一个老海员 雷斯垂德
And old sailor,Le Strade,
一个时运不济的人
who had fallen upon hard times.
我在检查火灾留下来的灰烬时
When I examined the ashes of that fire,
发现你的专家们漏掉了这个
I discovered that your experts had missed this.
一只尖利的白色牙齿
It is a tooth of the great white shark,
你能看到它上面有轻微雕琢过的痕迹
and you see that it has been lightly carved.
显然是海员的随身装饰物
It is typical of the work carried out by seamen.
但这并不足以证明
Well, this isn't evidence enough
在火灾里丧命的就是他
to show who died in the fire.
我很确定周一
I know for certain that on Monday,
谋杀案发生的前一天
the day before the murder,
一个流浪汉来过这里
a tramp called at this house.
然而 我盘问女管家的时候
Yet, when I questioned the housekeeper,
她向我保证
she assured me
这里绝不可能欢迎流浪汉
that no such tramp would ever be welcome.
但实际上不但好好接待了那个流浪汉
Not only was his reception welcoming,
还把奥德克先生的几件旧衣服给他了
but the man received some of Oldacre's clothing.
昨天在前门附近
Yesterday,near the front gate,
我发现了他留下了的记号
I found the calling card that he left,
用暗号通知流浪的同伴
a coded sign advising his fellow travelers
这里有慷慨的施舍
of a charitable welcome.
昨天晚上
And last night,
在你手下的本地警士帮助下
with the help of your local Constable,
我和其中一个流浪者谈过
I talked to one of these fellow travelers,
他说那个不幸的海员
who said that the unfortunate seaman
第二天又被请回去了
had been asked to call back the following day
说会有更殷勤的款待
with the assurance of further hospitality.
因此 之后那天早上
And so,the next morning,
他穿着新衣服
wearing his new clothes,
至少是穿着新裤子 折返那里...
or at least his new trousers, he returned ...
从此再也没有人见过他
and was never seen again.
你拯救了一个无辜人的性命 福尔摩斯先生
You've saved an innocent man's life, Mr. Holmes.
还挽救了我 给我免去了一场丑闻
You've also saved me some embarrassment.
啊 我的好兄弟
Ah, my good chap!
你会发现自己
You will find that your reputation
在此案后名声大振
has been enormously enhanced.
只要把你写的报告
Just make a few alterations to that report
稍加改动
which you are writing,
他们就会觉得想要蒙骗
and they will understand how hard it is
雷斯垂德巡官的眼睛有多么难啊
to throw dust in the eyes of Inspector Le Strade.
你不希望报告中有你的名字?
You don't want your name to appear?
一点也不
Not at all.
工作本身就是奖赏
His work is its own reward.
我会等着看你上绞架的!
I'll see you hang for this!
这话该是我说的
That privilege must surely be mine.
破烂熊字幕组
-==http://www.ragbear.com==-
欢迎加入